[
    {
        "question": "He is (<em>strang</em>) #### ðonne ic⁠ — He is stronger than I",
        "correctAnswer": "strengra",
        "explanation":"The stem of 'strang' undergoes i-mutation to become 'streng', but it isn't modifying a noun so it takes the 'ra' suffix to become 'strengra'",
        "commonMistakes": [
            {
                "incorrectAnswer": "strengran",
                "explanation": "Comparatives only decline if they are modifying a noun. This adjective is not modifying a noun, so it becomes 'strengra'"
            },
            {
                "incorrectAnswer": "strangra",
                "explanation": "The stem of 'strang' undergoes 'i-mutation' so the 'a' becomes 'e', meaning 'strang' becomes 'strengra' in the comparative"
            }
        ]
    },
    {
        "question": "Bebead he ðæt him mon (<em>lang</em>) #### cwidas beforan cwæde, and he symle gedefelice æftercwæþ⁠ — He ordered longer sayings to be spoken before him, and he always repeated them properly",
        "correctAnswer": "lengran",
        "explanation":"The stem of 'lang' undergoes i-mutation to become 'leng', and it takes the 'ran' suffix to become 'lengran' as comparatives decline weak if they are modifying a noun",
        "commonMistakes": [
            {
                "incorrectAnswer": "langran",
                "explanation": "The stem of 'lang' undergoes 'i-mutation' so the 'a' becomes 'e', meaning 'lang' becomes 'lengran' in the comparative"
            },
            {
                "incorrectAnswer": "lengra",
                "explanation":"Here 'lang' takes the 'ran' suffix to become 'lengran' as comparatives decline weak if they are modifying a noun"
            },
            {
                "incorrectAnswer": "langra",
                "explanation":"The stem of 'lang' undergoes i-mutation to become 'leng', and it takes the 'ran' suffix to become 'lengran' as comparatives decline weak if they are modifying a noun"
            }
        ]
    },
    {
        "question": "Ic in wite sceal bidan in bendum ond me (<em>god</em>) #### ham for oferhygdum æfre ne wene⁠ — I must in tormen abide in bonds, and never hope for any better home for my pride",
        "correctAnswer": "beteran",
        "explanation":"The adjective 'god' is irregular and so becomes 'beteran' in the comparative when modifying a noun",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Se horshwæl biþ micle (<em>lytel</em>) #### ðonne oðre hwalas⁠ — The walrus is much smaller than other whales",
        "correctAnswer": "læssa",
        "explanation":"The adjective 'lytel' is irregular and so becomes 'læssa' in the comparative when not modifying a noun",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Ic towurpe mine bernu and ic wyrce (<em>micel</em>) #### bernu⁠ — I will tear down my barns and I will build bigger barns",
        "correctAnswer": "maran",
        "explanation":"The adjective 'micel' is irregular and so becomes 'maran' in the comparative when modifying a noun",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Ðæt læstede þa xix wintra þa hwile þe Stephne cyning wæs one æfre hit wæs (<em>yfel</em>) #### ond wiersa⁠ — That lasted 19 winters while Stephen was king and ever it was worse and worse",
        "correctAnswer": "wiersa",
        "explanation":"The adjective 'yfel' is irregular and so becomes 'wiersa' in the comparative as it is not modifying a noun",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Næfre he ær ne siððan (<em>heard</em>) #### hæle fand⁠ — Never before or since did he find a stouter warrior",
        "correctAnswer": "heardran",
        "explanation":"Here 'heard' takes the 'ran' suffix as it is modifying the noun 'hæle'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Wisa, hwilc cræft þe geþuht betwux þas (<em>furðre</em>) #### wesan⁠ — Teacher, which craft do you think is the greater?",
        "correctAnswer": "furþra|furðra",
        "explanation":"Here 'furðre' loses its 're' and takes the 'ra' suffix to become 'furðra', as it is not modifying a noun",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Se wudu is eastlang and westlang hund twelftiges mila lang oððe (<em>lang</em>) ####⁠ — The wood, from east to west, is twelve hundred miles long or longer",
        "correctAnswer": "lengra",
        "explanation":"The stem of 'lang' undergoes i-mutation to become 'leng', and it takes the 'ra' suffix to become 'lengra', as it is not directly modifying a noun",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Ðam (<em>mild</em>) #### cyninge Wihtræde rixigendum⁠ — In the reign of the kindest king Wihtræd",
        "correctAnswer": "mildostan",
        "explanation":"Here 'mild' takes the superlative suffix 'ost' and the weak suffix 'an', as it comes after the definitive article 'þam' ",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Se lichoma ðonne on ðone (<em>heard</em>) #### stenc and on ðone fulostan biþ gecyrred⁠ — The body then shall be turned to the strongest and foulest stench",
        "correctAnswer": "heardostan",
        "explanation":"Here 'heard' takes the superlative suffix 'ost' and the weak suffix 'an', as it comes after the definitive article 'ðone'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Cwædon ðæt he wære manna (<em>mild</em>) #### and monþwærost⁠ — They said that he was kindest and most courteous of men",
        "correctAnswer": "mildost",
        "explanation":"Here 'heard' takes the superlative suffix 'ost' and no suffix",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "He sohte fram ðam ieldestan oþ ðone (<em>geong</em>) ####⁠ — He searched from the eldest to the youngest",
        "correctAnswer": "gingestan",
        "explanation":"The stem of 'geong' undergoes i-mutation to become 'ging', and takes the superlative suffix 'est' and the weak suffix 'an', as it comes after the demonstrative pronoun 'ðone'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Ic gyrne fultum ðinre foreþingrædene ðu (<em>halig</em>) #### mægden and þrowystr⁠ — I earnestly impolore your help, you holiest maiden and martyr",
        "correctAnswer": "haligoste",
        "explanation":"Here 'halig' takes the superlative suffix 'ost' and the strong accusative feminine suffix 'e' as it is modifying 'mægden'",
        "commonMistakes": [
            {
                "incorrectAnswer": "haligost",
                "explanation": ""
            }
        ]
    },
    {
        "question": "Se wæs on lare and on dæde se (<em>heah</em>) ####⁠ — He was in learning and in deed the highest",
        "correctAnswer": "hiehsta",
        "explanation":"The stem of 'heah' undergoes i-mutation to become 'hieh', and takes the superlative suffix 'st' and the weak nominative masculine suffix 'a', as it comes after the demonstrative pronoun 'se'",
        "commonMistakes": [
            {
                "incorrectAnswer": "hiehost|hiehest",
                "explanation":"Because 'heah' ends in a 'h', it drops the vowel in 'ost' to take the superlative suffix 'st'. Since it modifies a weak nominative masculine noun, it also takes the suffix 'a'"
            }
        ]
    },
    {
        "question": "He me sealde ðæt (<em>god</em>) #### hors⁠ — He gave me the best horse",
        "correctAnswer": "betest",
        "explanation":"The adjective 'god' is irregular, becoming 'betest' in the superlative. It takes no suffix because 'hors' is neuter and neuter accusative nouns have no suffix",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Sceall beon se (<em>lytel</em>) #### dæl nyhst þæm tune ðe se deada man on lið⁠ — The smallest portion shall be closest to where the dead man lies",
        "correctAnswer": "læsta",
        "explanation":"The adjective 'lytel' is irregular, becoming 'læst' in the superlative. It takes the weak nominative masculine ending 'a' to become 'læsta', as it comes after the demonstrative pronoun 'se'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Hit is ealra wyrta (<em>micel</em>) ####⁠ — It is greatest of all herbs",
        "correctAnswer": "mæst",
        "explanation":"The adjective 'micel' is irregular, becoming 'mæst' in the superlative. It takes no suffix",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Se deofol sloh lob mid ðære (<em>yfel</em>) #### wunde⁠ — The devil slew Job with the worst of wounds",
        "correctAnswer": "wierstan",
        "explanation":"The adjective 'yfel' is irregular, becoming 'wierst' in the superlative. It takes the weak genitive feminine ending 'an' to become 'wierstan'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    }
]